الغزاوية، قرية سورية تقع في آخر الجزء الجنوبي من منطقة عفرين
وتتبع لها.
Al-Ghazawiyah is a Syrian village located in the
southernmost part of the Afrin region and is affiliated with
it.
وهي تحاذي جبل سمعان من الجهة الشمالية الشرقية.
It borders Mount Simeon from the northeastern side.
وتبعد عن مدينة دارة عزة 11 كيلومتراً شمالاً وترتبط بها
تجارياً.
It is located 11 kilometers north of the city of Darat Izza
and is commercially connected to it.
تقع على الطريق الذي يربط منطقة عفرين مع مدينة حلب عبر دارة
عزة في ريف حلب الغربي.
It is situated on the road connecting the Afrin region with
the city of Aleppo via Darat Izza in the western countryside
of Aleppo.
تبلغ مساحة القرية 1500 هكتار،
The area of the village is 1,500 hectares,
وتسقي بساتينها وسهولها من نهر عفرين،
and its orchards and plains are irrigated by the Afrin
River,
عن طريق قنوات تجر إليها المياه من قرية برج عبدالو الواقعة
شمال الغزاوية.
through canals that draw water to it from the village of
Burj Abdalo, located north of Al-Ghazawiyah.
لا يعرف تاريخ دقيق لتأسيس القرية، ولكن معظم المصادر ترجع سكن
الإنسان فيها إلى ما قبل 500 عام كحد أقصى.
The exact date of the village's founding is unknown, but
most sources trace human settlement there back to a maximum
of 500 years ago.
يعمل القسم الأعظم من السكان بالزراعة وخاصة زراعة الحبوب
والفواكه والرمان، ويشتهر سكانها بصناعة دبس الرمان.
The vast majority of the population works in agriculture,
especially cultivating grains, fruits, and pomegranates, and
its residents are famous for making pomegranate molasses.
وقد تحررت من ميليشيات قسد في عام 2018.
It was liberated from the SDF militias in 2018.
في الغزاوية تتساوى المرأة مع الرجل في كافة مناحي الحياة
وخاصة في التعليم والعمل.
In Al-Ghazawiyah, women are equal to men in all aspects of
life, especially in education and work.
مجتمع الغزاوية مجتمع زراعي بسيط،
The community of Al-Ghazawiyah is a simple agricultural
society,
يعتمد على الزراعة البعلية والمروية من نهر عفرين بشكل أساسي
في حياته.
that relies primarily on rain-fed and irrigated agriculture
from the Afrin River for its livelihood.
لا تكاد تميز بين الأكراد الإيزيديين والمسلمين والعائلة
العربية الموجودة هنا،
You can hardly distinguish between the Yazidi Kurds, the
Muslims, and the Arab families present here,
بسبب الانسجام الكبير والتعايش السلمي التي عاشته هذه القرية،
due to the great harmony and peaceful coexistence this
village has experienced,
على مدى سنوات طويلة وعقود من عمرها القديم الجديد.
over many long years and decades of its ancient and modern
history.
سنكون معكم في هذه الفقرة في جولة في أحياء وحارات الغزاوية،
وأيضاً في سوقها التجاري. تابعونا.
We will be with you in this segment on a tour through the
neighborhoods and alleys of Al-Ghazawiyah, as well as its
commercial market. Stay with us.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله وبركاته، الحمد لله.
And upon you be peace, the mercy of Allah, and His
blessings. Praise be to Allah.
نتعرف عليك؟
May we know your name?
أنا المحامي أحمد شيخو مصطفى، من أهالي بلدة الغزاوية.
I am the lawyer Ahmed Sheikho Mustafa, from the people of
the town of Al-Ghazawiyah.
أهلاً وسهلاً فيك. خلينا نمشي هيك شوي ونحكي شوي عن الغزاوية.
Welcome. Let's walk a bit and talk a little about Al-
Ghazawiyah.
أهلاً وسهلاً، مية سلامة، حليت البركة.
Welcome, a hundred greetings, you brought a blessing.
الله يسلمك يا رب. أستاذي احكي لي شوي هيك عن وضع الناس هون،
شلونهم؟
May Allah keep you safe. Sir, tell me a bit about the
people's situation here, how are they?
وضع الناس، وضع طبيعي جداً.
The people's situation is very normal.
وضع محبة وإخاء وسلام، بلدة الغزاوية بلدة المحبة والسلام.
A situation of love, brotherhood, and peace. The town of Al-
Ghazawiyah is the town of love and peace.
المحبة والسلام؟
Love and peace?
أيوة. بلد زراعي بحت، يعتمد بشكل أساسي على الزراعة، الرمان.
Yes. A purely agricultural town, relying primarily on
agriculture, pomegranates.
من بساتين وفواكه وخضار، وكل أنواع الخضراوات.
From orchards, fruits, vegetables, and all kinds of
vegetables.
بمية الراحة، وبمية السد، بواسطة سواقي تجي من برج عبدالو.
With flowing water, and dam water, through canals coming
from Burj Abdalo.
يعني بالأصل معظم سكان القرية بيعتمدوا على الزراعة؟ ما في مهن
ولا حرف؟
So originally, most of the village's residents rely on
agriculture? Are there no professions and crafts?
بيعتمدوا شوي على التجارة كمان أيضاً، والدكاكين والدنيا،
وفيها كل شيء يعني.
They also rely a bit on trade, shops, and life in general;
it has everything.
تجارة شو؟
Trade of what?
تجارة الرمان، تجارة الحبوب، تجارة الدخان، تجارة الخضراوات،
Trade in pomegranates, trade in grains, trade in tobacco,
trade in vegetables.
يعني بيعتمدوا اعتماد يعني بالمية عشرين على التجارة.
I mean, they rely... about 20% on trade.
في حدا يعني مهاجر برا القرية؟ قديش نسبة المهاجرين؟
Is there anyone who migrated outside the village? What is
the percentage of migrants?
والله في، البيوت كلها هون، بس نسبة الشباب اللي رايحين لبرا
للدراسة وما دراسة،
Well, there are, the houses are all here, but the percentage
of youth who have gone abroad for study and things like
that,
يعني رايحين مشان الدراسة والعمل وشغلات هيك من هالنوع.
they went for studying, work, and things of that sort.
شقد يعني اللي رايحين؟
How many, I mean, have left?
والله نسبة يعني نسبة الشباب بالمية 40، أكثر من 40، مهاجرين
لبرا.
Well, the percentage of youth is about 40%, more than 40%
have migrated abroad.
بسبب الدراسة، بسبب العمل، بسبب قلة الشغل هون، يعني هيك شيء.
Because of studies, because of work, because of the lack of
jobs here, things like that.
طيب هلا أنا شايف قدامي، باعتبار عم تحكي لي على البيوت...
Okay, now I see in front of me, since you're talking to me
about the houses...
شايف قدامي بيت جميل كتير.
I see a very beautiful house in front of me.
هذا بيت، بيت العيلة، مؤلفة من خمس عائلات كانوا ساكنين فيها.
This is a house, the family house, made up of five families
who used to live in it.
بيت عائلتكم؟
Your family's house?
إي، عائلة لإلنا، بيت حج شيخو.
Yes, our family, the house of Haj Sheikho.
طيب، ممكن ندخل عليه؟ نشوف نمط البناء؟
Okay, can we go in? See the building style?
تفضل، أهلاً وسهلاً، مية سلامة.
Go ahead, welcome, a hundred greetings.
يلا.
Let's go.
أستاذي هلا نحنا وصلنا للبيت تقريباً.
Sir, now we have almost reached the house.
أيوة هذا البيت، بيت العائلة. كان فيها ساكنين خمسة، حالياً
فيها ثلاث بيوت.
Yes, this house, the family house. Five used to live in it,
currently there are three households.
ساكنين بهالبيت، ثلاث عوائل.
Living in this house, three families.
بيت عوائل يعني؟
A house of families?
ساكنين مع بعضهم، هنن إخوتي.
Living together, they are my brothers.
هلا هذا النمط اللي رح نشوفه جوا، هو نموذج البيت يعني
التقليدي، الاعتيادي، في الغزاوية؟
Now, this style that we will see inside, is it the model of
a traditional, regular house in Al-Ghazawiyah?
في هيك شكل بيوت، أيوة، بيت اعتيادي، العالم كلها بتيجي لهون.
There are houses in this shape, yes, a regular house,
everyone comes here.
كان بيت كبير الضيعة يعني، هو والدي كان كبير الضيعة.
It was the house of the village elder, I mean, my father was
the village elder.
يجتمعوا العالم هون، والمضافات والشغلات، يعني ماشي.
People would gather here, in the guest rooms and all, so it
went.
مضافات بيت الوالد، البيت الكبير، كبير بالعمر، كانوا يحترموه
ويعزوه.
The guest rooms of my father's house, the big house, the
elder, they used to respect and honor him.
قديش عمر هالبيت هاد؟
How old is this house?
هذا البيت بـ 1936 هيك شي، 1930، عام 1930.
This house is from 1936 or so, 1930, the year 1930.
مبنى كلو دفعة وحدة ولا على مراحل؟
Was it built all at once or in stages?
لا، على مراحل. عدة غرف، هي أقدم شي، وهي بعدين لبسوها
وحدثوها.
No, in stages. Several rooms, this is the oldest part, and
later they clad it and modernized it.
أظن في طابق الثاني كمان.
I think there is a second floor too.
نطلع لفوق شوي؟ نشوف الضيعة من فوق؟
Shall we go up a bit? See the village from above?
ماشي، أهلاً وسهلاً، يا رب.
Alright, welcome, oh Lord.
خلينا نقرب لهون شوي ونشوف الضيعة من فوق.
Let's get closer here a bit and see the village from above.
تفضل، هي الضيعة كلها هيك، بتشرف ع الضيعة والبساتين.
Go ahead, this is the whole village like this, it overlooks
the village and the orchards.
ع الخضراوات والأراضي.
Over the vegetables and the lands.
بما إنك، هلا واضح قدامنا نحن هون البساتين اللي صايرة شمالي
القرية.
Since you... Now it's clear in front of us here, the
orchards that are north of the village.
نعم، هون كفرزيت.
Yes, here is Kafr Zeit.
كفرزيت هديك الضيعة اللي ع الجبل اسمها كفرزيت؟
Kafr Zeit, that village on the mountain is called Kafr Zeit?
شمال الغزاوية، شمالي غربي.
North of Al-Ghazawiyah, northwest.
وأيضاً الباسوطة بتصير شمالاً مباشرة.
And also Al-Basouta is directly north.
برج عبدالو، كمان شمالي شرقي، والباسوطة.
Burj Abdalo, also northeast, and Al-Basouta.
وواضح أيضاً حتى في أراضي زراعية، واضحة هون؟
And it's also clear there are agricultural lands, visible
here?
نعم نعم في أراضي، انقعلت كان شو اسمه، بتعرف الرمان.
Yes, yes, there are lands, they were uprooted, you know,
pomegranates...
يعني إيراده قليل جداً، ولذلك العالم قلعوا الشجر مشان يزرعوا.
Its yield is very low, and therefore people uprooted the
trees to plant...
هي بالفترة الأخيرة؟
Was this recently?
بالفترة الأخيرة.
In the recent period.
هاد الجبل؟
This mountain?
هاد الجبل تابع للأحراش، هاد جبل ليلون اسمه.
This mountain is part of the forests, this mountain is
called Mount Lilon.
جبل ليلون يحد الغزاوية من الطرف الغربي.
Mount Lilon borders Al-Ghazawiyah from the western side.
ومن الطرف الهاد كلو جبل يعني، جنوب شرق ليلون.
And from this side it's all a mountain, I mean, southeast of
Lilon.
يحدها ليلون، وهون كمان بحسبوها ليلون، امتداد جبل قلعة سمعان.
It's bordered by Lilon, and here too they consider it Lilon,
an extension of the mountain of Saint Simeon's Citadel.
أيوة قبلي شرقي كلو جبال.
Yes, south, east, it's all mountains.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May Allah give you health.
مية سلامة، بدك شي تاني؟
A hundred greetings, do you need anything else?
بدي سلامتك.
Just your safety.
الله يعطيكن العافية، وشكراً جزيلاً لطاقم حلب اليوم.
May Allah give you health, and thank you very much to the
Halab Today crew.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام.
And upon you be peace.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May Allah give you health.
عافاك الله يا رب فيك، أهلاً وسهلاً.
May Allah give you health too, welcome.
شلونك؟
How are you?
الحمد لله.
Praise be to Allah.
نتعرف عليك؟
May we know your name?
أهلاً وسهلاً، أنت من هون ولا نازح؟
Muhammad Abu Fadi.
Welcome, are you from here or displaced?
لا، أنا من الغزاوية.
No, I am from Al-Ghazawiyah.
الغزاوية نفسها؟
From Al-Ghazawiyah itself?
إي أنا أصلي من الغزاوية بس كنت ساكن بحلب بس رجعت ع الضيعة.
Yes, I am originally from Al-Ghazawiyah, but I was living in
Aleppo, then I returned to the village.
ع الضيعة، أهلاً وسهلاً فيك.
To the village, welcome.
هلا أنت شايفك عم بتبيع سمانة، وعم بتبيع خضرا، ولبن وخبز،
وبتاع كلو.
Now, I see you are selling groceries, vegetables, yogurt,
bread, and everything.
إي، الحمد لله.
Yes, praise be to Allah.
طيب، شلون وضع الناس هون؟
Well, how is the situation of the people here?
الحمد لله كويس وضع الناس. يعني ماشي الحال.
Praise be to Allah, the people's situation is good. I mean,
it's okay.
قوتهم الشرائية شلونها؟
How is their purchasing power?
والله مو زيادة.
Well, not that great.
فقر يعني؟
Poverty, you mean?
يعني شايف أنت، كل شي رخيص، الرمان رخيص، الخضرة رخيصة.
I mean, you see, everything is cheap, pomegranates are
cheap, vegetables are cheap.
هلا عندك الخضرة هون رخيصة؟ شقد البندورة؟
Now, are vegetables cheap here? How much are tomatoes?
بندورة بـ 250.
Tomatoes are 250.
إنه هنن، الزراعة عم نزرعها يعني كل شي عم نبيعه رخيص، وشايف
أنت؟
It's that they... the agriculture we plant, I mean,
everything we sell is cheap, and you see?
أنت عم تحكي ع الزراعة رخيصة؟
Are you saying agricultural products are cheap?
نعم، هون الأوضاع هون هلا هون البندورة، العالم عم بتبيعها بـ
250.
Yes, here the situation is... now here tomatoes, people are
selling them for 250.
الأسعار شلون؟ قياساً لغيركم؟
How are the prices? Compared to others?
لا كويسة، الأسعار يعني ماشي حالها، مو غالية غالية، هلا
بالنسبة لبندورة شتوية وبندورة بـ 250 يعني مقبولة.
No, they are good, the prices are, I mean, acceptable, not
too expensive. Now, for winter tomatoes, tomatoes at 250 is
acceptable.
تفاح؟
Apples?
تفاح بـ 250.
Apples are 250.
خيار قديش؟
How much are cucumbers?
خيار والله اليوم بـ 300 ما نزلنا.
Cucumbers, to be honest, today they are 300, we didn't bring
any down.
ما نزلت. باقي أسعار، باقي أسعار، مثلاً الخبز، الزيت...
You didn't bring any down. The rest of the prices, other
prices, for example, bread, oil...
لا الخبز يعني رغم الغلا، يعني الربطة بـ 200 عم نبيعها، ما
غليت.
No, bread, despite the inflation, I mean, we are selling a
bundle for 200, it hasn't gone up.
يعني وضع النازحين أحسن ولا وضع أهل الضيعة؟
I mean, is the situation of the displaced better or the
people of the village?
والله تقريباً كلو يعني، متل بعضه.
Well, almost everything is, I mean, the same.
متل بعضه؟ شو بيشتغلوا النازحين هون؟
The same? What do the displaced people work in here?
النازحين يعني كلياتهم هون، ناس ع الغنم، ناس عم تاخد أراضي
تزرعها.
The displaced, I mean, all of them here, some tend sheep,
some are taking land to farm.
غنم عندهم هنن أغنام قطعان؟
Sheep? Do they have flocks of sheep?
إي هنن جايين لما نازحين جايين معهم أغنام.
Yes, when they came as displaced people, they brought sheep
with them.
وعم بيستأجروا أراضي؟
And they are renting lands?
ناس إي عم تستأجر، وناس عم بتشارك على، مثلاً أهل الضيعة عندهم
أراضي بياخدوا منهم شركة، بيزرعوا معهم بالشركة، وما بعرف شو.
Some people, yes, are renting, and some are partnering, for
example, the people of the village have lands, they take it
as a partnership, they plant with them in partnership, and I
don't know what.
مثلاً أهل الضيعة ما في عندهم عمال.
For example, the people of the village don't have workers.
هنن هدول النازحين عندهم عمال، وما بعرف إيش، بيزرعوا شركة. في
ناس تزرع لحالها.
These displaced people have workers, and I don't know what,
they plant as a partnership. There are people who plant on
their own.
في ناس مثلاً تيجي معها، في معها عملة، تاخد أراضي لحالها
بتزرع ع حسابها.
There are people, for example, who come with money, they
take lands on their own and plant at their own expense.
هذا اللبن اللي أنا شايفه، إنت مختره ولا...؟
This yogurt that I see, did you ferment it or...?
لا، هاد مشتريه من هدول... هدول الناس تبع العرب الشوايا.
No, I bought this from those... those people of the Arab
Shawaya.
قديش السطل عندك؟
How much is the bucket you have?
هاد الكيلو عم نبيعه، هاد معز، يعني شوي مريق، عم نبيعه بـ 400
الكيلو.
This kilo we sell... this is goat's milk, so it's a bit
thin... we sell it for 400 per kilo.
عم تغليه كتير؟
Are you selling it very expensively?
لا والله هيك عم نشتريه.
No, to be honest, that's how we buy it.
والبقر قديش؟
And cow's milk? How much?
البقر 250 لـ 300.
Cow's milk is 250 to 300.
الغنم؟
Sheep's milk?
الغنم 550.
Sheep's milk is 550.
500.
أسعارك واوا شوي؟
Are your prices a bit high?
إي واوا وأنا عم بشتري غالي، يعني من حط ع... يعني مثلاً مربح
شي بسيط ومنبيع.
Yes, they are, and I am buying it expensively, I mean, we
add... I mean, for example, a simple profit margin and we
sell.
طيب، الله يرزقك.
Alright, may Allah bless your livelihood.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May Allah give you health.
على راسي، أهلاً وسهلاً.
I'm just joking with you.
You're very welcome, welcome.
لا يزيد عمر الغزاوية عن الـ 500 عام، وفق ما قاله معظم
المؤرخين الذين كتبوا عن هذه القرية.
The age of Al-Ghazawiyah does not exceed 500 years,
according to what most historians who wrote about this
village have said.
القرية كانت إلى ما قبل حوالي 100 سنة من الآن، عبارة عن أراضٍ
زراعية منبسطة، تروى من وادي نهر عفرين.
Until about 100 years ago, the village was a flat
agricultural land irrigated by the Afrin River valley.
زرعت بأشجار الرمان في فترة متأخرة، لا تزيد عن 50 سنة من
الآن.
It was planted with pomegranate trees recently, no more than
50 years ago.
قبل 100 سنة من الآن، كانت البيوت معظمها من الخيام.
A hundred years ago, most of the houses were tents.
قيل أن سبب تسمية الغزاوية بهذا الاسم يعود لسببين؛
It is said that the reason for naming Al-Ghazawiya this name
is due to two reasons;
أحد المؤرخين قال سبب التسمية يعود بسبب انتشار أسماء لعائلات
الغزي في قرية الغزاوية وفي القرى المجاورة، وهذا أحد
الاحتمالات.
One historian said the reason for the name is due to the
spread of the names of the Al-Ghazzy families in the village
of Al-Ghazawiya and the neighboring villages, and this is
one of the possibilities.
الاحتمال الثاني أن الغزاوية سميت نسبة إلى مالكة هذه القرية
قبل حوالي 300 عام، السيدة غزالة مندي، وهي من الديانة
الإيزيدية.
The second possibility is that Al-Ghazawiya was named after
the owner of this village about 300 years ago, Mrs. Ghazala
Mandi, who is of the Yazidi religion.
للحديث عن تاريخ الغزاوية يسرنا أن نلتقي بالأستاذ أحمد الحسن،
أحد رجال الغزاوية الكبار والعارفين بتاريخها. يلا معنا.
To talk about the history of Al-Ghazawiya, we are pleased to
meet Mr. Ahmed Al-Hassan, one of the elder men of Al-
Ghazawiya and those knowledgeable about its history. Let's
go.
أستاذ أحمد، أنت من أحد أكبر الرجال في القرية واللي حافظين
تاريخ الغزاوية.
Mr. Ahmed, you are one of the oldest men in the village who
have memorized the history of Al-Ghazawiya.
تحكي لي عن أهمية موقع الغزاوية، واللي بتعرفه عن تاريخها.
Tell me about the importance of Al-Ghazawiya's location, and
what you know about its history.
موقع الغزاوية تابعة لعفرين، 15 كيلومتر جنوبي عفرين.
The location of Al-Ghazawiya is affiliated with Afrin, 15
kilometers south of Afrin.
نعم. قديش بعيدة عن قلعة سمعان؟
Yes. How far is it from the Citadel of Simeon?
عن قلعة سمعان 6 كيلومتر.
It is 6 kilometers from the Citadel of Simeon.
قديش؟
How much?
6 كيلومتر.
6 kilometers.
عن قلعة سمعان؟
From the Citadel of Simeon?
إيوه.
Yes.
باتجاه الشمال إيوه.
Towards the north?
Towards the north, yes.
نعم. قديش عمر القرية؟
Yes. How old is the village?
عمرها شي 400 سنة.
It is about 400 years old.
كيف؟ إيمت تأسست؟ مين أسسها؟ عدد سكانها؟
How? When was it founded? Who founded it? What is its
population?
عدد سكانها 1800 نسمة.
Its population is 1800 people.
حالياً.
Currently.
حالياً، 1800 نسمة.
Currently, 1800 people.
احكي لي كيف تأسست يعني؟
Tell me how it was founded?
بيسكنوا فيها طائفتين؛ طائفة الإسلام والطائفة الإيزيدية.
It is inhabited by two sects; the Islamic sect and the
Yazidi sect.
اثنين مع بعض، محبين مع بعض، بالسراء والضراء، بالأفراح
متعاونين مع بعض، وبالأحزان متعاونين مع بعض. ما في عندنا
تفرقة نهائياً.
Both together, loving each other, in good times and bad
times, in weddings cooperating with each other, and in
sorrows cooperating with each other. We don't have any
division at all.
طيب تمام. تاريخ الضيعة، إيمت أقدم شي بتعرفوا للضيعة هون؟
Okay, great. The history of the village, what is the oldest
thing you know about the village here?
أقدم شي ضيعة الغزاوية هون...
The oldest thing in the village of Al-Ghazawiya here...
هون بهالمنطقة بالذات؟
Here in this specific area?
الضيعة كلها يعني...
The whole village...
عند الجامع؟
Near the mosque?
عند الجامع، هي أقدم شي. لأنه كان في هنيك خان...
Near the mosque, it's the oldest. Because there used to be a
khan there...
بس ما بقي آثار إله؟
But there are no traces left of it?
ما بقى آثار، سووه جامع هلا فوق سووه...
No traces left, they made it into a mosque now...
هلا صار فوقه جامع؟
Now there's a mosque on top of it?
إي.
Yes.
مين سكن أول شي هون؟
Who lived here first?
سكنوا أول شي طائفة الشيخ لاريه.
The first to live here were the Sheikh Lari sect.
طائفة الشيخ لاريه؟
The Sheikh Lari sect?
شيخ لاريه، هم من طوائف شيخ مند الإيزيدية.
Sheikh Lari, they are from the sects of Sheikh Mand of the
Yazidis.
من وين إجوا؟
Where did they come from?
من هون، ساكنين... ما بعرف من وين إجوا بس أنا بعرف ساكنين هون
من 400 سنة.
From here, living... I don't know where they came from but I
know they've been living here for 400 years.
من وين إجوا ما بتعرف؟
You don't know where they came from?
نعم.
Yes.
وبعدها؟
And then?
بعدها تطورت، إجوا غير طوائف لهون، وصاروا يأخذوا الأراضي،
واشتروا أراضي وسكنوا هون.
Then it developed, other sects came here, and they started
taking lands, they bought lands and lived here.
بس أقدم طائفة هون طائفة الشيخ لاريه.
But the oldest sect here is the Sheikh Lari sect.
الشيخ لاريه.
The Sheikh Lari.
طيب، لما إجوا الشيخ لاريه لهون، بنوا بيوت من طين وخشب
وسقفوهن ولا كانوا ساكنين بخيام؟ كيف سكنوا؟
Well, when the Sheikh Lari came here, did they build houses
of mud and wood and roof them, or were they living in tents?
How did they live?
على ما أعتقد كانوا بخيام. خيام عادية.
I believe they were in tents. Normal tents.
بعدين تطوروا شوي يعني، فوق الصاج ما صاج، بعدين صاروا بالطين،
بالطين تبع...
Then they developed a bit, with tin roofs, then they started
using mud...
معناها باعتبار كانوا بالخيام، كانوا معناها يعتمدوا على
الرعي؟
This means since they were in tents, they relied on grazing?
إي رعي... رعي الحيوانات.
Yes, grazing... grazing animals.
لأنه هون البرية كان الأراضي ما في، كلها بور، ما في حدا.
Because the wilderness here, there were no lands
(cultivated), it was all barren, nobody was there.
ما كان في شجر؟
There were no trees?
لا، في رجال بس ما في حدا، رعيان بيرعوا فيها.
No, there were men but nobody (farming), shepherds grazing
in it.
بقصد ما كان في شجر، ما كانت مشجرة؟
I mean there were no trees, it wasn't planted with trees?
لا ما في.
No, there wasn't.
ليش؟ إيمت شجرت الأراضي؟
Why? When were the lands planted?
لأنه ما كان في مي.
Because there was no water.
لك وين المي كانت؟ مي برج عبدالو ونهر عفرين...
Where was the water? The water of Burj Abdalo and the Afrin
River...
بعدين إجوا شركة... شركة الأرمن فتحوا القناة، وصاروا يسقوا
الأراضي.
Then an Armenian company came, they opened the canal, and
started irrigating the lands.
إيمت الأرمن إجوا لهون فتحوا القناة وجابوا المي للضيعة؟
When did the Armenians come here and open the canal and
bring water to the village?
تقريباً بعام 1955 أو 53 هيك إجوا.
Around 1955 or 1953, they came.
يعني الغزاوية كانت عبارة عن أرض زراعية غير مروية حتى عام
1955 لما إجت شركة أرمنية...
So Al-Ghazawiya was just un-irrigated agricultural land
until 1955 when an Armenian company came...
من حلب.
From Aleppo.
من حلب، فتحوا قناة من نهر عفرين من برج عبدالو لقرية
الغزاوية.
From Aleppo, they opened a canal from the Afrin River from
Burj Abdalo to the village of Al-Ghazawiya.
من برج عبدالو للغزاوية، إيوه.
From Burj Abdalo to Al-Ghazawiya, yes.
طيب شقد نسبة الأرض المشجرة هون؟
Well, what is the percentage of planted land here?
إي والله كثير، ما بقول لك لا. يعني كل مزارع عنده 10 هكتارات،
عنده 15 هكتار...
Oh, a lot, really. I mean, every farmer has 10 hectares, has
15 hectares...
المقصود مثلاً ثلثين الأراضي مزروعة، مشجرة بالأشجار؟
Meaning, for example, two-thirds of the lands are
cultivated, planted with trees?
إي مزروعة بأشجار إي.
Yes, planted with trees, yes.
إي والله.
Oh wow.
طيب، هلا أنا حسب ما فهمت منك، وإنه أنت عندك يعني في بيتك في
غرفة قديمة كثير.
Well, from what I understood from you, you have a very old
room in your house.
هي نموذج للبناء الأول في القرية من حوالي 100 سنة.
It is a model of the first buildings in the village from
about 100 years ago.
إيوه.
Yes.
خلينا نشوفها.
Let's see it.
تفضل. شرف.
Go ahead. Welcome.
عمي هلا هيدي الغرفة؟
Uncle, is this the room now?
إي هالغرفة إي.
Yes, this room, yes.
قديش عمرها هي؟
How old is it?
عمرها تقريباً 150 سنة.
It is about 150 years old.
50؟
50?
150.
من إيش مبنية تحكي لي؟
Yes.
What is it built of, can you tell me?
مبنية من حجار ومن تراب.
Built of stones and dirt.
تراب. وجوا سقفها من شو؟
Dirt. And inside, what is its roof made of?
جوا كمان نفس الشي، طلينا بالطين، طين أحمر وتراب.
Inside it's also the same, we coated it with mud, red mud
and dirt.
طين أحمر وكلس. خلينا ندخل عليها شوي.
Red mud and lime. Let's go inside a bit.
هلق هون، عمو شرف، لهون. مشان الكاميرا تشوف.
Now here, uncle, come here. So the camera can see.
هلق واضح إنه هذا، هذا تراب.
Now it's clear that this, this is dirt.
إيوه.
Yes.
هذا كلس إي.
And this is lime.
This is lime, yes.
آه، وهذا السقف؟
Ah, and this roof?
سقف خشب وورق بردي نحن بنقول له.
The roof is wood and papyrus leaves, we call it.
ورق بردي. هذا بيطلع على أطراف النهر.
Papyrus leaves. That grows on the banks of the river.
إيوه.
Yes.
أيوه. والأرض؟
I see. And the floor?
والأرض كانت تراب، طيناها طبقة إي وبعدين هيك سويناها.
And the floor was dirt, we added a layer to it, yes, and
then we made it like this.
وكمان سمداراني أو رفوف...
And also storage niches or shelves...
إي، رفوف قديمة.
Yes, old shelves.
رفوف قديمة كثير يعني.
Very old shelves.
إيوه، على زمن قديم. كانوا يحطوا فيها صحون ما صحون.
Yes, from old times. They used to put plates and things in
them.
إيمت تركتها أنت لهي الغرفة ما بقت تنام فيها؟
When did you leave this room and stop sleeping in it?
وقت ما توفى والدي.
When my father passed away.
من كم سنة يعني؟
How many years ago?
يعني شي 10، 12 سنة.
Around 10, 12 years ago.
10، 12 سنة؟
10, 12 years?
إيوه.
Yes.
الله يرحمه.
May God have mercy on him.
يلا، الله يعطيك العافية يا عم.
May God have mercy on you.
Alright, may God give you health, uncle.
الله يعافيك، أهلاً وسهلاً.
May God give you health, welcome.
لما بنحكي عن الغزاوية، لازم نحكي عن الرمان.
When we talk about Al-Ghazawiya, we must talk about
pomegranates.
الرمان هو خلاصة حكاية الغزاوية.
Pomegranates are the essence of the story of Al-Ghazawiya.
ربما كانت الغزاوية والباسوطة هما القريتان الأشهر في زراعة
الرمان في منطقة عفرين وربما في كامل سوريا.
Perhaps Al-Ghazawiya and Al-Basuta are the two most famous
villages for growing pomegranates in the Afrin region, and
perhaps in all of Syria.
بهالفترة من السنة بيصادف موسم قطاف الرمان، واللي بيتزامن
أيضاً مع موسم قطاف الزيتون.
At this time of the year, it coincides with the pomegranate
harvest season, which also coincides with the olive harvest
season.
رايحين معكم هلق لنزور إحدى العائلات اللي عم تقوم بتصنيع دبس
رمان، لنتعرف على حكاية الرمان ودبس الرمان في الغزاوية.
We are going with you now to visit one of the families that
is making pomegranate molasses, to learn about the story of
pomegranates and pomegranate molasses in Al-Ghazawiya.
تفضلوا معنا.
Please join us.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
على البركة.
And upon you be peace.
Blessings upon you.
شلونكم؟
Welcome.
How are you?
الله يعطيكم العافية.
Thank God, thanks to you.
May God give you strength.
نتعرف عليكِ؟
May God give health to your heart.
Can we get to know you?
موليدة سيدو.
Mawlida Sido.
أهلاً وسهلاً فيكِ. وهون؟ الأخت...
Welcome to you. And here? Sister...
فاطمة يوسف.
Fatima Youssef.
فاطمة يوسف، أهلاً وسهلاً فيكِ.
Fatima Youssef, welcome to you.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
والأخوات شو عم يساووا هون؟ نتعرف عليكِ؟
And the sisters, what are they doing here? Can we get to
know you?
مزكين أحمد شيخ ملو.
Mizgin Ahmed Sheikh Mallo.
أهلاً وسهلاً فيكِ. هلا شو عم تساووا؟
Welcome to you. Now, what are you doing?
عم نساوي دبس رمان يعني.
We are making pomegranate molasses.
دبس رمان.
Pomegranate molasses.
إيوه.
Yes.
إيوه. أنتم مشهورين بدبس الرمان بالغزاوية؟
I see. Are you famous for pomegranate molasses in Al-
Ghazawiya?
إيوه، مشهورين.
Yes, we are famous for it.
مشهورين كثير. إيش اللي بيميز دبس الرمان بالغزاوية عن غير
مناطق؟
Very famous. What distinguishes pomegranate molasses in Al-
Ghazawiya from other areas?
كل مناطق بيعملوا دبس رمان هيك يعني.
All areas make pomegranate molasses like this.
إي بس ليش هون أطيب؟
Yes, but why is it tastier here?
إي رمانات هون أطيب يعني. الرمان بيطلع أطيب إي.
Yes, the pomegranates here are tastier. The pomegranates
turn out tastier, yes.
أيوه. شو أنواع الرمان اللي عم تشتغلوا فيه، هذا الرمان شو
هذا؟
I see. What types of pomegranates are you working with, what
is this pomegranate?
هذا نوعه فرنسي، لون فرنسي نعمله إي.
This type is French, French color we make, yes.
هذا فرنسي.
This is French.
هي فرنسي إيوه.
This is French, yes.
أيوه. ما بتسووا رمان بلدي مثلاً؟ ما بتسووا دبس رمان من
الرمان البلدي؟
I see. Don't you use local pomegranates, for example? Don't
you make pomegranate molasses from local pomegranates?
هلا بصير، بلدي بصير.
Well it works, local works.
بس الفرنسي أطيب؟
But the French is tastier?
فرنسي أطيب منه بيطلع.
French turns out tastier than it.
شو بتكون نوعية دبس الرمان؟ يعني كيف بتكون؟ مثلاً أسماك،
أمرق، أنكه، كيف بتكون؟
What is the quality of the pomegranate molasses like? I
mean, how is it? For example, thicker, thinner, more
flavorful, how is it?
هيك بيطلع يعني، نوعيته، بنغليه على النار.
It turns out like this, its quality, we boil it on the fire.
تغلوه على النار. طيب هلا الرمان...
You boil it on the fire. Well now, the pomegranates...
هذا رمان.
This is a pomegranate.
إي.
Yes.
هذا اللي ورانا، هدول اللي ورانا شو هدول؟ أنا لفت نظري هدول،
شو هدول؟
This one behind us, these ones behind us, what are they?
They caught my attention, what are these?
هي رمان، حطينا بالصابور هي.
These are pomegranates, we put them in the Sabour.
شو يعني صابور؟
What does Sabour mean?
يعني صابور حط...
I mean Sabour, put...
حط صابور يعني، حطيناه بالصابور يعني.
Put in Sabour, we put it in the Sabour.
إيش بتحطوا؟ كيف بتحطوه؟ كيف يعني صابور؟ يعني تخزين؟
What do you put? How do you put it? What does Sabour mean?
Does it mean storage?
لا، حط على الأرض، في فلينات وبنحط عليها.
No, put it on the ground, there are foam boxes and we put it
on them.
ليش مغطينه بإيش؟ مغطينه بالقش؟
What is it covered with? Covered with straw?
بالقش غطيناه نحن إيوه.
We covered it with straw, yes.
ليش؟ خلينا نشوفه شوي.
Why? Let's see it a bit.
إي خالة تعالي فرجيه، خالة تعالي فرجيه.
Yes aunt, come show him, aunt, come show him.
خليها تروح معك.
Let her go with you.
هدول شو هدول؟
What are these?
هدول صابورات.
These are Sabours.
شو يعني صابورات؟
What do Sabours mean?
هون عم نحوش الرمان، نحطه تحت الحيش وما هيش عشان المطر ما
يأثر عليه شيء.
Here we harvest the pomegranates, we put them under the
weeds and stuff so the rain doesn't affect them.
ولبين ما يجي وقته بنطالعه من الصابور.
And until its time comes, we take it out of the Sabour.
يعني بتخلوه لحتى مثلاً يختمر أكثر؟ يستوي أكثر؟
Do you leave it so that, for example, it ferments more?
Ripens more?
إي يستوي أكثر، يختمر أكثر شوي.
Yes, ripens more, ferments a bit more.
ولا لحتى يبيعوه، بس يرتفع سعره، يبيعوه بسعر أعلى؟
Or until they sell it, when its price goes up, they sell it
at a higher price?
لا هيك، هو أسعار السعر كمان يعني. لبين ما يجي سعر كويس كمان
يبيعوه.
No, it's like that, it's also about the prices. Until a good
price comes, they sell it.
ولبين ما هو كمان يستوي. مو مثل الشجرة يعني يعيفوه كله بيطقطق
وهيك شيء بيصير.
And until it also ripens. It's not like the tree, if they
leave it, it all cracks and things like that happen.
هذا اسمه صابور.
This is called Sabour.
اسمه صابور هذا.
صابور. هلا على سيرة الرمان، خلينا نروح على سيرة الصابور،
خلينا نروح نشوف شلون عم يفرطوا الرمان.
Sabour. Now speaking of pomegranates, let's go, speaking of
the Sabour, let's go see how they extract the pomegranate
seeds.
وهون عندك كله مشان الدبس رمان صاير هيك.
And here you have it all for the pomegranate molasses, it's
like this.
طبعاً كله بالشجر صاير هيك، كله مطقطقين...
Of course, it all became like this on the trees, all
cracked...
بالشجرة مطقطق الرمان؟ شو السبب، ليش؟ المطر؟
The pomegranates cracked on the tree? What's the reason,
why? Rain?
ما في مطر، الأولي ما في مطر بيصيروا هيك. بيطقطقوه هيك.
There's no rain, at first there's no rain, they become like
this. They crack like this.
لأنه مو شربانين مي كثير بيطقطقوا هيك. ولبين ما نحن نجيبه
لهون ومثل ما شايف عينك.
Because they haven't drunk much water, they crack like this.
And by the time we bring it here, as your eyes can see.
هلق كأنه خلصوا المصروفين اللي عم يشتغلوا هون؟
Now it seems the workers who are working here have finished?
إي لكان، مصروفين هلق، العمال راحوا هلق.
Yes of course, finished for now, the workers have left now.
خلينا نقرب لهم شوي. هدول عمال هون بيفرطوا الرمان.
Let's get a bit closer to them. These workers here extract
the pomegranate seeds.
إي، من الساعة 7 عم يجوا، للساعة 2 إي بيروحوا هن.
Yes, they come from 7 o'clock, until 2 o'clock, yes, they
leave.
هيدي كوم، كلها هيدي رمان.
This is a pile, all of this is pomegranate.
هذا كوم وعندك هنيك كوم.
This is a pile and you have a pile there.
هلق هذا ملاحظ أنه هذا أحمر، وهذا أحمر. وكأنه هيك شايف شيء
أخضر، غير لون؟
Now I notice that this is red, and this is red. And it seems
I see something green, a different color?
إي هنيك لفان هذا.
Yes, that one there is Laffan.
لفان.
Laffan.
لفان. دبس الرمان بيصير... هذا امبارحة خلصناه...
Laffan. The pomegranate molasses becomes... We finished this
yesterday...
امبارحة خلصناه هنيك. وهذا صار وقته لهون كمان عم نشتغل فيه.
Yesterday we finished over there. And this one's time has
come here, we are working on it too.
هذا كله فرنسي؟
Is this all French?
كله فرنسي هذا عندك.
This is all French here.
امم. بس دبس الرمان ما بيصير من لفان أو من حامض؟
Mmm. But can pomegranate molasses be made from Laffan or
sour pomegranates?
لا بيصير، من نفس الشيء. من الفرنسي كمان بيصير، من اللفان
كمان بيصير.
No, it works, the same thing. From the French it also works,
from the Laffan it also works.
Dibis rumman. Bas mayyet el fransi mo metl mayyet el laffan.
Pomegranate molasses. But the French juice isn't like the
Laffan juice.
Hallaq rah nshuf. Dibis rumman el fransi rah ysawwuu.
Tfaddalu ma'na.
Now we will see. They are going to make the French
pomegranate molasses. Please, go ahead.
El mayye el fransi biseer lono ahmar.
The French juice turns red.
El rumman haada el laffan, mayto btseer abyad.
This Laffan pomegranate, its juice turns white.
Ya'ni mo metl el fransi btseer. W ta'mto mo metl ta'met el
fransi.
It doesn't turn out like the French one. And its taste is
not like the French taste.
Tamam. Byikhtilif 'andon el ta'me.
Okay. The taste differs then.
Tamam.
Okay.
Hallaq hon qabl shi haada el mafrout. Haada shu rah tsawwu
fi el mafrout?
Now here, first of all, this separated stuff. What are you
going to do with the separated seeds?
Habb el rumman. Hallaq hiyye 'am t'assiro.
Pomegranate seeds. Now she's squeezing them.
Shlon 'am t'assiro?
How is she squeezing them?
B rejlayha 'am t'assiro.
She's squeezing them with her feet.
Ya'ni bthuttu el rumman haad b qalb kees?
So you put these pomegranates inside a sack?
Eh mnfaddih b qalb el kees w hiyye 'am t'assir, btitla' mayy
mn hon w mnhutto 'a nar. Biseer dibis 'andak.
Yes, we empty them into a sack, and she squeezes them. The
juice comes out from here, and we put it on the fire. You'll
get molasses.
Shqad bitawwil el 'amaliyye ma'ek?
How long does the process take you?
Ya'ni shi rbi' sa'a.
About a quarter of an hour.
Rbi' sa'a bt'assirih hek?
You squeeze it for a quarter of an hour like this?
Eh rbi' sa'a.
Yes, a quarter of an hour.
Taba'an kil kees rbi' sa'a ha.
Of course, each sack takes a quarter of an hour.
Eh.
Yes.
Mshan el mushahideen bas lazim ya'rifu inno haada el jirin
mu'aqqam w maghsul.
Just so the viewers know, this basin is sterilized and
washed.
Lakan.
Of course.
W el jazme taba'ik?
And your boots?
Ndife, ma msta'milnaha, bas lal shighel. Eh.
They're clean, we haven't used them, just for work. Yes.
Ma btinzli inti?
Don't you go down (to stomp)?
La ma banzel ana.
No, I don't go down.
Tbaqqi rbi' sa'a hek?
Do you keep doing it for a quarter of an hour like this?
Eh. Haada fransi. Eh rumman fransi haad.
Yes. This is French. Yes, this is French pomegranate.
Hallaq intu da'iman btitbkhooh 'a nar, 'a hatab walla...?
Now, do you always cook it over a fire, over firewood,
or...?
Eh 'a hatab.
Yes, over firewood.
'A hatab. Eh 'a hatab. Tayyib. Ba'd ma... yislamu ideyki.
Over firewood. Yes, over firewood. Okay. After... Bless your
hands.
Allah ysallmak ya rab.
May God bless you.
Ba'd ma thuttooh 'a nar shqad bitawwil 'a nar?
After you put it on the fire, how long does it stay on the
fire?
Ya'ni sa'ateyn tlath sa'at arba' sa'at... hasab el nar.
Two, three, four hours... depends on the fire.
Tayyib, ba'd ma yighli?
Okay, after it boils?
Mnfaddih. Bitbakhkhar el mayy, laben ma tiqtal el mayy
ba'den mnfaddih.
We empty it. The water evaporates, until it thickens, then
we empty it.
Btfaddooh. Btnashfooh walla shlon bthuttooh fawran?
You empty it. Do you dry it, or how do you put it
immediately...?
La, bismak el mayye la halo hiyye bl akheer bismak biseer
dibis rumman. Bismak 'a nar huwwe shwayye shwayye bismak.
No, it thickens. The juice itself thickens in the end and
becomes pomegranate molasses. It thickens on the fire,
little by little it thickens.
Bas ma btdifoolo shi?
But you don't add anything to it?
La. Wala shi.
No. Nothing at all.
Mileh leymoun kaza?
Lemon salt or something?
La la la... Mayy 'al hill.
No, no, no... Just the juice.
W bthuttooh bl anani w btbee'o. Aywa. W byitkhazzan, shqad
bitkhazzan haad?
And you put it in bottles and sell it. I see. And it gets
stored, how long can this be stored?
Ya'ni b sneen bdall ma'ak w ma byitsharrak.
It can last with you for years and doesn't spoil.
Sneen.
Years.
Eh ma byitsharrak. Ma biseerlo shi.
Yes, it doesn't spoil. Nothing happens to it.
Shu el aklat illi bthuttoola dibis rumman? Bthuttoolo dibis
rumman?
What dishes do you put pomegranate molasses in? Do you put
pomegranate molasses in them?
Wallah ana 'an zaat nafsi ma bhuttillo shi.
Honestly, I personally don't put it in anything.
Laysh?
Why?
Ma bhubbo.
I don't like it.
Mezgin shu tqilili ta'i shway... 'a el akil.
Mezgin, what do you say, come here a little... about the
food.
Shu el aklat illi bthuttoola dibis rumman?
What dishes do you put pomegranate molasses in?
Eh ma hutt 'alayha shi bas dibis rumman.
Yes... I don't put anything on it, just pomegranate
molasses.
Shu el aklat illi bthuttila dibis rumman inti?
What dishes do you put pomegranate molasses on?
Haada. Hitti 'ala zaytoon biseer, 'a kubbe biseer, 'a
salatat biseer.
This. Put it on olives, it works. On kibbeh, it works. On
salads, it works.
'A lahme b'ajeen, 'al bilbol.
On meat with dough (lahmacun), on bulgur.
Aywa kil shi biseer ya'ni.
Yes, it works with everything.
W el kubbe el maqliyye? Kubbe maqliyye.
And fried kibbeh? Fried kibbeh.
La ma mnhuttola.
No, we don't put it on it.
Intu ma bthuttola.
You don't put it on it.
La nahn ma mnhutt 'alayha. 'A kubbe, salatat, zaytoon hutt
'alayha, biseer.
No, we don't put it on it. It works on kibbeh, salads,
olives, put it on them, it works.
Allah ya'tikom el 'afiye.
May God give you strength.
Allah y'afik inshallah.
May God give you strength too.
Shukran ilkon.
Thank you all.
Ma' ghroob shames haaza el yawm el kharifi, el mushmis w el
mumtir,
With the sunset of this sunny and rainy autumn day,
tintahi jawlatuna fi qaryat el Ghazawiyye fi reef Afrin el
janoubi.
our tour in the village of Ghazawiya in the southern
countryside of Afrin comes to an end.
Sanakoon ma'akum fil asabi' el qadima fi jawlat jadida min
manatiq souriyya ukhra habiba.
We will be with you in the coming weeks in a new tour from
other beloved Syrian regions.
Li mutaba'at barnamijina, tabi'u safhat el face el khass bil
qanat w aydan mawqi'na 'ala el internet, Halab Today TV dot
net.
To follow our program, follow the channel's specific
Facebook page, and also our website on the internet, Halab
Today TV dot net.
Assalamu alaykum w rahmatullahi w barakatuh.
Peace, mercy, and blessings of God be upon you.